<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  ex:ts=4:sw=4:sts=4:et
  -*- tab-width: 4; c-basic-offset: 4; indent-tabs-mode: nil -*-
-->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
                      "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <title>OpenEmbedded User Manual</title>
        <authorgroup>
            <corpauthor>OpenEmbedded Team</corpauthor>
        </authorgroup>
        <copyright>
            <year>2006</year>
            <holder>Holger Hans Peter Freyther</holder>
        </copyright>
        <legalnotice>
            <para>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution License. To view a copy of this license, visit <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/</ulink> or send a letter to Creative Commons, 559 Nathan Abbott Way, Stanford, California 94305, USA.</para>
        </legalnotice>
    </bookinfo>


    <chapter>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <section>
            <title>Overview</title>
            <para><ulink url="http://www.openembedded.org">OpenEmbedded</ulink> is a set of metadata used to crosscompile, package and install software packages. OpenEmbedded is being used to build and maintain a number of embedded Linux distributions, including OpenZaurus, Familiar and SlugOS.</para>
        <para>The primary usecase of OpenEmbedded are:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>Handle crosscompilation.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Handle interpackage dependencies</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Must be able to emit packages (tar,rpm,ipk)</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Must be able to create images and feeds from packages</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Must be highly configurable to support many machines, distribution and architectures.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Writing of metadata must be easy and reusable</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>Together with <ulink url="http://bitbake.berlios.de/manual">BitBake</ulink> OpenEmbedded satisfies all these and many more. Flexibilitiy and power have always been the priorities.</para>
        </section>


       <section>
            <title>History</title>
            <para>OpenEmbedded was invented by the creators of the OpenZaurus project. 
At this time the project had pushed <emphasis>buildroot</emphasis> to the limits. It supported the creation of
<emphasis>ipk</emphasis>, feeds and images and had support for more than one machine. But it was impossible
to use different patches, files for different architectures, machines or distributions. To overcome this shortcoming
BitBake and OpenEmbedded were created.</para>
       </section>
    </chapter>


    <chapter>
        <title>Metadata</title>
        <section>
            <title>File Layout</title>
            <para>OpenEmbedded has three directories holding BitBake metadata <emphasis>conf</emphasis>,
<emphasis>classes</emphasis> and <emphasis>packaes</emphasis>. FIXME</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Syntax</title>
            <para>OpenEmbedded has files ending with <emphasis>.conf</emphasis>, <emphasis>.inc</emphasis>,
<emphasis>.bb</emphasis> and<emphasis>.bbclass</emphasis>. The syntax and semantic of these files are best
described in the <ulink url="http://bitbake.berlios.de/manual">BitBake manual</ulink>. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Classes</title>
            <para>OpenEmbedded provides special BitBake classes to ease compiling, packaging and other things. FIXME.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Writing Meta Data (Adding packages)</title>
            <para>FIXME, ask koen to fill in things here</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>


    <chapter>
        <title>Getting OpenEmbedded</title>
        <section>
            <title>Getting BitBake</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Getting OpenEmbedded</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Configuring OpenEmbedded</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Building Software</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
        <title>Common Usecases/tasks</title>

        <section>
            <title>Creating a new Distribution</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Adding a new Machine</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Adding a new Package</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Creating your own image</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Using a prebuilt toolchain to create your packages</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Using a new package format</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
        <title>Comparsion</title>

        <section>
            <title>buildroot</title>
            <para>We are better, they are on crack?</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>crosstool</title>
            <para>We are better, they are on crack?</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>handmade</title>
            <para>Crosscompilation is a tough business. It is not that crosscompiling is hard itself but many people misuse
the buildsystem they use to build their software. This will lead to a variety of issues you can run into. This can be failing
tests on configuration because of executing cross compiled binaries or crashes at runtime due wrong sizes of basic types. 
When utilizing OpenEmbedded you avoid searching for patches at many different places and will be able to get things done more quickly.
OpenEmbedded allows you to chooose from a pool of ready to use software packages, allow creation of images and many more.</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
