<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section id="distutils_class" xreflabel="distutils class">
  <title>distutils class</title>

  <para>Distutils is a standard python system for building and installing
  modules. The <emphasis>distutils</emphasis> class is used to automate the
  building of python modules that use the distutils system.</para>

  <para>Any python package that requires the standard python commands to build
  and install is using the distutils system and should be able to use this
  class:<screen>python setup.py build
python setup.py install</screen></para>

  <para>The <emphasis>distutils</emphasis> class will perform the build and
  install actions on the <command>setup.py</command> provided by the package,
  as required for building distutils packages, including setting all the
  required parameters for cross compiling. It willl also perform the following
  actions:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Adds python-native to <command>DEPENDS</command> to ensure that
      python is built and installed on the build host. This also ensure that
      the version of python that is used during package creation matches the
      version of python that will be installed on the target.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Adds python-core to <command>RDEPENDS</command> to ensure that the
      python-core is installed when this module is installed. Note that you
      need to manually add any other python module dependencies to
      <command>RDEPENDS</command>.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>The following example from the <emphasis>moin</emphasis> recipe shows
  how simple this can make a python package:<screen>DESCRIPTION = "A full fledged WikiWiki system written in Python"
LICENSE = "GPL"
SECTION = "base"
PRIORITY = "optional"
MAINTAINER = "Your name &lt;yname@example.com&gt;"
PR = "r1"

SRC_URI = "${SOURCEFORGE_MIRROR}/moin/moin-${PV}.tar.gz"

inherit distutils</screen>The header, source location and the inherit are all
  that is required.</para>
</section>